Guide to the Mario Paci Papers M1917
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Mario Paci papers
1897-2002
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Paci, Mario
Zaharoff, Floria Paci
Zaharoff, Alex
M1917
3 Linear Feet: 2 manuscript boxes, 3 flat boxes, 1 map folder
Articles, correspondence, photographs, drawings, programs, newspaper clippings, and musical scores and compositions related to the pianist and conductor Mario Paci (1878-1946), who founded the Shanghai Symphony orchestra.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research and must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical note
Mario Paci was born in Florence on 4 June 4, 1878. He studied piano at the Conservatorio di Musica S. Pietro a Majella in Naples, under the tutelage of Giovanni Sgambati in Rome, and conducting and composition at the Conservatorio di Musica Giuseppe Verdi in Milan. After winning the Franz Liszt Prize in 1895 he performed frequently on piano throughout Europe. In 1918 on an Asian tour, he arrived in Shanghai, where he remained several months due to a severe illness. He eventually was approached to form an orchestra to perform European works for the large community of Western businessmen and government officials living in Shanghai at the time. He reorganized the Shanghai Symphony Orchestra in 1919, augmented by players whom he recruited primarily from Italy with the support of the Shanghai Municipal Council. The orchestra was the first major introduction of Western music into the cultural life of China. The audiences and the orchestra were both composed entirely of Europeans, but Paci gradually opened up membership in the orchestra, and eventually the audience, to native Chinese despite considerable opposition from local authorities and officials.
Paci also taught music to Chinese living in Shanghai, and also aided Cai Yuanpei to establish the National School for Music in 1927, which became the Shanghai Conservatory of Music in 1956. When the Japanese occupied China in World War II, Paci was forced to resign as conductor, which eventually led to the dissolution of the orchestra. Paci was unable to continue his career as a musician in China and died on August 3, 1946. Paci was a tyrannical conductor known for his temper in rehearsals, but he is credited with raising the level of musical performance to a high degree in Asia, where Western music had no tradition and was generally not known or practiced except by foreigners.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Floria Paci Zaharoff and Alex Zaharoff, 2012-2017.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence to and from Paci and his family, including his first wife, soprano Elizabeth Mackenzie, his second wife Sara (Hillen) Paci, and his daughter, Floria (Paci) Zaharoff. There are also articles, concert programs, documents, photographs, drawings, newspaper clippings, manuscript compositions by Paci, and published musical scores dedicated to Paci by fellow musicians. There are also drafts for Floria Paci Zaharoff's book "The daughter of the maestro: life in Surabya, Shanghai and Florence."
Conductors (Music) -- Italy -- Biography.; Conductors (Music) -- China -- Biography.; Conductors (Music) -- Biography.; Zaharoff, Floria Paci; Paci, Mario; Shanghai jiao xiang yue tuan; Zaharoff, Floria Paci; Zaharoff, Alex
- Mario Paci: articles (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Mario Paci: correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Floria Paci: correspondence (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Floria Paci Zaharoff. Correspondence with Cai and Melvin, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Programs Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Programs, 1901-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Programs, 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Programs, 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- newspaper clippings - translations (Box 1, Folder 9)
- newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- newspaper clippings, 1902-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- newspaper clippings (photocopies) (Flat-box 3, Folder 1)
- Mario Paci: fliers, announcements etc. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Academia Santa Caecilia Document, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- The China Critic (see p. 455: Triumphs of Mario Paci), 1933-05-04 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Robert Bickers. "The Greatest Cultural Asset East of Suez." offprint (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Floria Paci Zaharoff. Book drafts (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Watercolor, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Mozart. Piano Concerto no. 20 in D major, K. 466. Cadenza by Mario Paci Piano part, annotated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Mozart. Piano Concerto no. 20 in D major, K. 466. Ms. parts, incomplete (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Insulinde for women's chorus and string orchestra (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Alla Menuetto for string orchestra (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Mario Paci. Alleluja for mixed chorus (4 voices) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Songs for Floria Zaharoff (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Mario Paci. "A la triste histoire" (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Mario Paci. "Heimwee" (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Mario Paci. "Ich bin so miid" (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Mario Paci. "Ich heb je lief" (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Mario Paci. "Im Volkston" (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Mario Paci. "Nacht" (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Mario Paci. "Panteismo" (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Mario Paci. "Sognai" (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Mario Paci. "Wier wuszten beide dasz es Sunde war" (Box 2, Folder 18)
- The 120th Anniversary Album of Shanghai Symphony Orchestra (1879-1999) (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Broadsheet-sized announcement (German): April 1, 1910, Leipzig. Performance, with Mario Paci, klavier. (Very fragile)., 1910-04-01 (Flat-box 3, Folder 2)
- Certificate of Qualification, Surabajan Art Society, July 7, 1910, announcing Mario Paci as a member of honour. [In Dutch, accompanying page has rough translation], 1910-07-07 (Flat-box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to Mario Paci (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Piano pedagogy and technical studies (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Carabella, Ezio. Andante con variazioni. Miniature score (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Casella, Alfredo. La donna serpente. Miniature score (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Parelli, Attilio. Symphony, C minor. Miniature score (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Rocca, Lodovico. Interludio Epico. Miniature score (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Vlachos, George T. V., Jr. My First Composition, dedicated to Paci (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Mario Paci (?) Broeders, vormt den Broeder-Keten. Ms. song (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Aaron Avshalomov. Imitations of Bach's Little Preludes and Fuges "in Chinese idiom" Ms (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Bach. Suites, cello, no. 3, C major arranged for piano by Leopold Godowsky, dedicated to Paci (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Beethoven. Sonatas, piano, op. 26, A-flat major. Dedication by (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Chopin. Preludes fingering by Cortot (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Lovreglio. 3 Etudes-Impromptu and Dessins Animés. Signed (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Riccardo Pick-Mangiagalli. Deux Lunaires (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Respighi. Notturno and Antiche danze ed arie arranged for piano (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Sgambati. Étude Mélodique, op. 21, no. 5 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- photographs - family & travel (Box 2, Folder 1)
- photographs, including some inscribed to Paci (Box 2, Folder 2)
- photograph from EJAS (Box 2, Folder 3)
- photographs (Box 4, Folder 3)
- photographs - dogs (Box 6, Folder 1)
- stereographs - 4 small portraits of woman (Box 6, Folder 2)
- page from scrapbook with 12 identified photographs (Box 6, Folder 3)
- photographs - Mario Paci (Box 6, Folder 4)
- stereographs - Paci and others in Java, Borobudur, Sumatra, etc. (some numbered) (Box 6, Folder 5)
- stereographs - one captioned Hong Kong 1921 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- stereographs - seaside (Box 6, Folder 7)
- stereographs - groups of people (Box 6, Folder 8)
- stereographs - children (Box 6, Folder 9)
- oversize (Map-folder 5)